Okay, let's talk for a minute about structure.
That's what I'm going to call it.
But what we're looking at is what needs to be in this one or two minutes with regards to material.
Well, regardless of where you find the monologue, if you put it together or even if you write it yourself, it is important that the monologue makes sense.
Don't think necessarily so much in the terms of beginning, middle and end.
But where are we going?
What is the through line of the character?
What is the character talking about?
Why are they talking about it?
Where is this monologue going?
Traditionally a monologue should have a climax.
And what a climax is, is where the character makes a revelation.
Throws somebody out.
Some big action occurs that they have been talking about prior to it.
So, think of the monologue structure as kind of an arc.
We're building to something, that big something happens and then we can taper it down.
Also, remember you only have one or two minutes to get the job.
To make the impression.
To be fabulous.
So always, always pick a monologue with a strong opening line.
Many monologues are more talking about something, just chatting.
And that's okay.
But you must have a strong opening line and really you need a strong closing line.
But that is not, the closing is not absolutely as imperative as the opening line. You want a STONG opening. HEY, LISTEN TO ME!!!
I AM GOING TO DO A MONOLOGUE!!!
And then your closing, the thing about the closing, the last line it should be very clear, I'm done.
I have seen way too many monologues that just kind of ended.
And left me, the director, wanting more.
Okay, that was it?
You never want to say, okay, I'm finished.
You want to come in with that strong line.
So that's what we got to have in this monologue.